so let's get so I'm going to now move
into the more serious talk so this is a
this is of course the picture it's
pretty famous to the Tower of Babel and
the idea of the Tower of Babel was of
course that we were trying to build this
massive structure to get up to the sky
to meet with God but we couldn't get our
act together down on earth and it would
God actually shattered this and
fragmented the languages and this is why
we have miscommunication but it's also a
measurement story and if you read the
story there's a lot of debate about how
do we measure and how do we build this
damn thing and this is the situation
we're in multiple fronts where
measurement is not interfacing with
reality anymore multiple fronts where a
false sense of reality is being created
and where power is overriding the
interest of the good so it's actually a
mutually amplifying crisis and it's a
crisis in the technical will barian
Harbor masse and kind of developmental
structural sense of the word which is to
say it's a crisis that demands either
vertical structural reorganization or
regression because it's not something
that we can't stay in this that's my
argument that this is one of those
turning points catastrophic bifurcation
so it's not a crisis like ah this really
sucks it's a crisis in a structural
sense and it's the structures of
measurement that need to change so if
we're talking about a post-capitalist
economy if we're talking about an
actually sustainable form of human
civilization we're talking about a
fundamentally different measurement
infrastructure at the basis of it that's
the claim so I'm going to run through
these crisises economics first so this
is a Berk share this is actually a form
of alternative currency that circulates
in the berkshires if you live in like
Great Barrington you can live most of
your life just circulating with these
forms of currency so you know it's
interesting that it's not a great model
it's owned by for-profit company it's
kind of cute you have to pay your taxes
of course in American dollars
but the idea that money is a fundamental
form of measurement it's very important
and one of the things that money does is
homogenized the measurement of value
right the neoliberal consensus that we
have has essentially said that there's
one way to measure value in the world
right and it is money
and I'm not going to get into kind of
Marxist theories of you know how that
distorts and alienates us but you can
see and we've all experienced it when
you take certain things for example like
child care and put a price on them it
becomes a different kind of thing
because you've quantified something that
is typically understood to be not
quantifiable and we're increasingly
invading the life world by turning it
into things that can have a price tag
right like the tragedy of capitalism in
one way is the idea that we have to put
a price on things that are priceless all
right and that's a measurement issue and
then of course there's just econometrics
which is like to my mind like one of the
most ridiculous Sciences so GDP is the
classic thing you'd see here and what
you'd see if you have this figure on GDP
is fluctuation but generally a rising
gross domestic product globally this is
called the Gini coefficient the Gini
coefficient is just as simple to produce
as GDP in a way but it tracks economic
inequality it tracks within country
economic inequality so what this says is
economic inequality has been going up
drastically since the 80s right but so
has GDP now which one do we value and
which one do we use in debates about
policy and which ones do we use to talk
about the health of national economies
GDP which oversimplifies and neglects
within country variability it's a basic
issue right and then there's all of
these things in economics that have to
do with the valuation and measurement of
risk right the main reason we had in
2007 an economic crisis was because
there's Finance ears were creating these
collateralized debt obligations and then
there were these rating agencies that
said those are dope investments like
they had a four point scale of
measurement of risk on investment in
there like this is higher yield they
were colluding with the finance seers to
basically extract wealth from extremely
vulnerable populations and then the
whole thing came crashing down but that
was about power colluding with measure
to distort
and to create a different and unjust
situation education this is my field
I've got a book coming out about
educational measurement and social
justice this is a picture of a testing
boycott in Seattle in 2013 and these
people are walking out and they're just
not doing it anymore to me this is one
of the most exciting things I've seen
and I'm in touch with these people and
there's a real growing movement to say
that the problem in educational reform
what's backing the marketization of the
privatization of education what's
backing the increasing use of psycho
tropics among school-age kids it mostly
can be brought down to the testing
infrastructure and a lot of that can be
brought down to what I just described
they need to put a price on what is
priceless right and the need to quantify
what has traditionally been
unquantifiable the need to take
something that we used to have for free
away from us and sell it back to us
right and this is what harbor mas talked
about as the invasion of the life world
by the system and one of the ways you do
that is by measuring measuring measuring
more of what used to not be measured
that we just not even think about
measuring and now we measure everything
that moves in education as well
environment right I mean environmental
measures are extremely contentious
political topic right and so this is one
of these maps that shows a distribution
of temperature change around the world
and this is an aggregate measure of tens
of thousands of measurement instances
each one of which has these parameters
of estimation around it there's actually
very complex epistemological object that
most people accept at face value right
there are huge regions where no measures
are taken at all and you know in a
complex dynamical system you need as
much measurement everywhere I'm not
saying this is bad science but I'm
saying that we don't actually know the
extent of the situation we're dealing
with because we have simple ways of
modeling extremely complicated
phenomenon this is and this relates to
the climate crisis this is a water meter
that you can put on your faucet and that
will tell you how much water you're
using in a day right and that seems like
a great idea and I agree that it is but
as the economic crisis deepens what
we're going to see is increasing policy
and increasing use of force
to bring measurement into the
distribution of scarce resources and so
I see a future where as the economic and
ecological crisis gets more complex our
lives get constrained in extremely
radical ways and most of that's going to
happen through measurement you know
people are you know think about your
electric meter you know so and this
they're gonna measure your water yeah
your water bill I mean they measure your
water but this is precise you know so uh
okay politics in another area where
measurement is a mess this is a poll
about political polls right that's how
it's gotten like and it's about what
polls do we trust and there's and I'm
not going to get into the details here
but my point is that political polling
is an incredibly crude way to get a
sense of the nature of what the people
are thinking it's the opposite of
participatory democracy it's a forced
choice equation where they give you
several options and you're forced to
pick one of them it's like a
standardized test right and so it's not
an insight into the people this is an
electronic voting booth right the voting
is one of the most basic forms of
measurement and created in the ancient
world they had all these systems from
the volume of applause to everyone
leaves a marble and a different bucket
as they leave the auditorium all these
they're ways to try to get a sense of
how do we measure the mood of the people
and participatory democracy is one thing
where you vote go/no-go is a very other
thing and I think we underestimate the
way that our political debates are
polarized simply as a result of the
basic technology that we use to make
democratic decisions which is again a
forced choice and standardized testing
called selected-response right
deliberative democracy is constructive
response they're not going to get it as
a distinction but it's very important to
think about a future where we do forms
of this political decision-making that
nothing to do with voting in any simple
way right now we have a form of politics
which is spectatorship and voting and it
models precisely advertising and
consuming and it's a very tight
relationship I mean the Super Bowl and
you know presidential campaign are sell
a lot of commercials so health right
this is the DSM everyone knows the DSM
it's been a little bit too funked but I
put it on here just as and just to kind
of put into the space there's this huge
and proliferating area of medical
diagnostics and medical diagnostic
technology and I'm not gonna say this is
good or bad that that's proliferating
but I'm gonna say that we have created
an incredibly complex medical
bureaucracy based fundamentally on
measures and we have a reductive sense
of the nature of disease so we have kind
of isolated forms of medical measurement
that really distort the full complexity
of the human so that's one aspect of
medical measurement and then this is the
Human Genome Project medical diagnostics
are actually about 10 to 15 years behind
where they could be if we were using
everything we knew about customized
medicine and genetics the main reason
that's the case I think is because we
have a for-profit health care industry
in the United States and you're never
gonna have a health care industry that
actually cures people and is for-profit
all right as simple as soon as you cure
someone they don't come back to give you
more money if you want to make money in
medicine you need to create chronic
dependence on disease right or drugs
that create side effects that you can
treat without the drugs which is what
happens so personality I love this thing
so this is the standardized service
worker and this is a White Castle
corporation thing for 1931 what's
interesting about this is you know
there's all the physical things you need
to do but here there's an arrow pointing
at his brain that says be ready to make
a suggestion so they're not even telling
you to just standardize the way you look
they're telling you to standardize your
mental state as a worker and so one of
the main organizations that I've got my
eye on is the international standards
organization which probably no one's
ever heard of so ISO 9000 they were
never heard of ISO 9000 yeah yeah yeah
so I have so 9,000 effects millions and
millions of people and none of those
people had to say in the creation of
this ISO 9000 essentially a massive
human resource
kind of management system so any huge
multinational has to follow the policies
of ISO 9000 and the people affected by
those policies have no idea and were
never consulted and if you look at the
way it was created in the nature of
international standards organization it
is built essentially as a way to control
labor and it was put in place again with
in the 70s so so that's the scary stuff
and that was very quickly and you read
my paper you can get more and I'm gonna
expand it into a book cuz I think it's a
it's a critical issue but you can see
that there's this complex compounding
crisis and it relates epistemology with
ontology and ethics and all of these
things together but it's grounding out
of the fact that if we created different
measures we would have a very different
world and if different measures have
been decided on at some prior point in
history the trajectory of where it would
be different so I want to talk about
like kind of preferable futures for
measurement so I think we need to
actually reconsider the nature of the
anthropocentric measurement systems you
know one of the things we lost with the
metric system was a system that made any
references to the dimensionality of the
human form and so that's why we have
massive impersonal forms of
infrastructure and alienating
standardized McMansions
and there's been a couple architects
who've pushed back about against this
and refused to use standard forms and
create their own anthropocentric forms
and you get much more beautiful
buildings so I think we have to
understand the value of the universal
measure but also think about the local
the particular and the human scale so
that's one thing I'm going to talk more
about this valorisation of the unique
and how important it is on a later slide
so the dynamics distance and complexity
is something I'm talking about here one
or two measures taken on one or two
variables once or twice is never enough
to understand the complex phenomenon
full-stop every phenomenon I was talking
about was a complex phenomenon that is
measured this way or worse